Welcome back to a push in under three
minutes. No time for intros. Let's get
into it. So, it's truly time to examine
the causes of the Civil War. At this
point, every compromise about slavery
has flopped. The Missouri Compromise
gone. The Compromise of 1850 made things
worse. So, now let's look at the final
attempts to hold this broken country
together and how they spectacularly
failed. The Kansas Nebraska Act got
passed, which allowed those states to
freely vote on whether they wanted to
allow slavery or not. And the funny
part, that whole Missouri compromise
line from earlier, it didn't matter
anymore because Nebraska was well above
that line. But what you should know
about this act is it caused thousands to
pour into these states to vote for their
own side, which led to what is called
bleeding Kansas, where everyone fought
in the streets and killed each other
over votes in Kansas. One of the people
famous here was an absolutely insane man
named John Brown, who was against
slavery and staged a slave rebellion at
Harper's Ferry before being killed by
the expertise of Robert E. Lee. The
chaos of bleeding Kansas and the spread
of slavery enraged anti-slavery
northerners leading to the formation of
the Republican party in 1854. But now
that we have all this, let's
contextualize and envision the world
right now. We know from the Constitution
that the US needs three branches of
government to function. So let's look at
each of them right now. First, the
executive. Leading up to the Civil War,
we see a collection of weak presidents
that did nothing truly notable to
address the issue of slavery. Okay, so
the executive branch is a no-go, but
let's try the legislative. Well, here in
the Senate, Charles Sunder gave a speech
against slavery, which caused a southern
congressman named Preston Brooks to beat
him within an inch of his life with a
cane. Okay, so the legislative is a
bust, but as long as we had the Supreme
Court, Dread Scott be Sanford. God damn
it. This case established that slaves
were not citizens and Congress could not
ban slavery in southern territories. So,
we have the executive branch being weak.
We have people caning each other on the
Senate floor in the legislative and
deplorable, sadistic rulings by the
Supreme Court. When you look at it this
way, it honestly is hard to think a war
couldn't have broken out. And I'll end
this video with a quote from the most
sane, reasonable, level-headed guy I can
think of, John Brown. Right before he
died, he said, quote, "I am now quite
certain that the crimes of this guilty
land will never be purged away, but with
blood." And guess what? He was right.
Because the Civil War started less than
2 years later. On the screen now are
some AP style questions for this topic.
Pause
now. I'll put the answers on the screen
now. I will see you on the next one.